<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Nectarian Randomness (Posts about gradual)</title><link>https://krsna-rand.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" href="https://krsna-rand.github.io/categories/gradual.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2019 08:24:05 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>SB:gradual:1/62</title><link>https://krsna-rand.github.io/posts/sb-1-gradual/</link><dc:creator>soul4krsna</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://krsna-rand.github.io/posts/sb-1-gradual/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (8 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>gradual</category><guid>https://krsna-rand.github.io/posts/sb-1-gradual/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2019 08:20:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>SB:gradual:39/62</title><link>https://krsna-rand.github.io/posts/sb-39-gradual/</link><dc:creator>soul4krsna</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Canto 3: Status Quo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Explanation of Devotional Service by Lord Kapila&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3.29.23&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;dvisatah para-kaye mam&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;manino bhinna-darsinah&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;bhutesu baddha-vairasya&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;na manah santim rcchati&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SYNONYMS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;dvisatah—of one who is envious; para-kaye—towards the body of another; mam—unto Me; maninah—offering respect; bhinna-darsinah—of a separatist; bhutesu—towards living entities; baddha-vairasya—of one who is inimical; na—not; manah—the mind; santim—peace; rcchati—attains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TRANSLATION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One who offers Me respect but is envious of the bodies of others and is therefore a separatist never attains peace of mind, because of his inimical behavior towards other living entities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PURPORT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this verse, two phrases, bhutesu baddha-vairasya (inimical towards other) and dvisatah para-kaye (envious of another’s bod), are significant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One who is envious of or inimical towards others never experiences any happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A devotee’s vision, therefore, must be perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He should ignore bodily distinctions and should see only the presence of the part and parcel of the Supreme Lord, and the Lord Himself in His plenary expansion as Supersoul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is the vision of a pure devotee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bodily expression of a particular type of living entity is always ignored by the devotee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is expressed herein that the Lord is always eager to deliver the conditioned souls, who have been encaged within material bodies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devotees are expected to carry the message or desire of the Lord to such conditioned souls and enlighten them with Krsna consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus they may be elevated to transcendental, spiritual life, and the mission of their lives will be successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course this is not possible for living entities who are lower than human beings, but in human society it is feasible that all living entities can be enlightened with Krsna consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even living entities who are lower than human can be raised to Krsna consciousness by other methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, Sivananda Sena, a great devotee of Lord Caitanya, delivered a dog by feeding him prasada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Distribution of prasada, or remnants of foodstuffs offered to the Lord, even to the ignorant masses of people and to animals, gives such living entities the chance for elevation to Krsna consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Factually it happened that the same dog, when met by Lord Caitanya at Puri, was liberated from the material condition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is especially mentioned here that a devotee must be free from all violence (jivahimsa).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lord Caitanya has recommended that a devotee not commit violence to any living entity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the question is raised that since vegetables also have life and devotees take vegetable foodstuffs, isn’t that violence? Firstly, however, taking some leaves, twigs or fruit from a tree or plant does not kill the plant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides that, jivahimsa means that since every living entity has to pass through a particular type of body according to his past karma, although every living entity is eternal, he should not be disturbed in his gradual evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A devotee has to execute the principles of devotional service exactly as they are, and he must know that however insignificant a living entity may be, the Lord is present within him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A devotee must realize this universal presence of the Lord.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>gradual</category><guid>https://krsna-rand.github.io/posts/sb-39-gradual/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2019 08:18:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Bg:gradual:9/14</title><link>https://krsna-rand.github.io/posts/bg-9-gradual/</link><dc:creator>soul4krsna</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Karma-yoga—Action in Kṛṣṇa Consciousness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;5.29&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;bhoktāraṁ yajña-tapasāṁ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;sarva-loka-maheśvaram&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;suhṛdaṁ sarva-bhūtānāṁ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;jñātvā māṁ śāntim ṛcchati&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://krsna-rand.github.io/posts/bg-9-gradual/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (2 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>gradual</category><guid>https://krsna-rand.github.io/posts/bg-9-gradual/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2019 08:11:04 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>